I have a friend in Portugal
لدي صديق في البرتغال
whose grandfather built a vehicle out of a bicycle
جده بنى سيارة من دراجة
and a washing machine so he could transport his family.
و غسالة ملابس ليستخدمها للتنقل
He did it because he couldn't afford a car,
صنعها لأنه لا يستطيع شراء سيارة
but also because he knew how to build one.
و لأنه يعرف كيف يصنع واحدة
There was a time when we understood how things worked
كانت هنالك وقت عرفنا فيه كيف تعمل الأمور
and how they were made, so we could build and repair them,
و كيف صنعت حتى نستطيع صناعتها وتصليحها
or at the very least
أو على الأقل
make informed decisions about what to buy.
كيف نتخذ قرار صحيح فيما نشتري.
Many of these do-it-yourself practices
الكثير من ممارسات اصلاح الأمور بأنفسنا
were lost in the second half of the 20th century.
قد تلاشت في النصف الثاني من القرن العشرين.
But now, the maker community and the open-source model
لكن الان مجتمع الصانع والنماذج مفتوحة المصدر
are bringing this kind of knowledge about how things work
تعيد هذا النوع من المعرفة الى حياتنا
and what they're made of back into our lives,
المعرفة حول كيف تعمل الاشياء ومم تصنع
and I believe we need to take them to the next level,
وانا اؤمن اننا نحتاج ان نأخذهم للمرحلة التالية
to the components things are made of.
الى المكونات التي تصنع منها الاشياء
For the most part, we still know
في اغلب الاحيان ما زلنا نعرف
what traditional materials like paper and textiles are made of
مم تصنع المواد التقليدية مثل الورق والاقمشة
and how they are produced.
وكيف يتم انتاجها.
But now we have these amazing, futuristic composites --
لكن الان لدينا هذه المركبات البلاستيكية المستقبلية المدهشة
plastics that change shape,
التي تغير شكلها,
paints that conduct electricity,
طلاء موصل للكهرباء,
pigments that change color, fabrics that light up.
الأصباغ التي تغير لونها، والأقمشة التي تضيء.
Let me show you some examples.
دعوني اريكم بعض الامثلة.
So conductive ink allows us to paint circuits
حبر موصل يمكننا من رسم الدوائر
instead of using the traditional
بدلا عن استخدام
printed circuit boards or wires.
لوحات الدوائر المطبوعة التقليدية او اسلاك.
In the case of this little example I'm holding,
في حالة هذا المثال الصغير الذي احمله,
we used it to create a touch sensor that reacts to my skin
استخدمناه لعمل حساس لمس يتفاعل مع الجلد
by turning on this little light.
بتشغيل هذا الضوء الصغير.
Conductive ink has been used by artists,
الحبر الموصل تم استخدامه من قبل الفنانين
but recent developments indicate that we will soon be able
لكن التطورات الحديثة تشير انه سيكون بامكاننا قريبا
to use it in laser printers and pens.
استخدامه في طابعات الليزر والاقلام.
And this is a sheet of acrylic infused
وهذه ورقة من الاكريليك
with colorless light-diffusing particles.
مشبعة بجزيئات مشتتة للضوء عديمة اللون
What this means is that, while regular acrylic
ما يعني هذا , في حين ان الاكريليك العادي
only diffuses light around the edges,
يشتت الضوء حول الحواف،
this one illuminates across the entire surface
هذه تضيء عبر السطح كاملا
when I turn on the lights around it.
عندما اشغل الاضواء حولها.
Two of the known applications for this material
اثنين من التطبيقات المعروفة لهذه المادة
include interior design and multi-touch systems.
تتضمن التصميم الداخلي وانظمة اللمس المتعدد
And thermochromic pigments
واصباغ الكروم الحرارية
change color at a given temperature.
تغير لونها على حسب درجة الحرارة.
So I'm going to place this on a hot plate
اذا انا سأضع هذا على طبق حار
that is set to a temperature only slightly higher than ambient
مضبوط على درجة حرارة اعلى قليلا من درجة حرارة المحيط
and you can see what happens.
ويمكنك رؤية ماذا يحدث.
So one of the principle applications for this material
اذا واحدة من التطبيقات المبدئية لهذه المادة
is, amongst other things, in baby bottles,
هي,ضمن اشياء اخرى, في زجاجات الاطفال,
so it indicates when the contents are cool enough to drink.
حتى تشير الى متى تكون المحتويات باردة كفاية لشربها.
So these are just a few of what are commonly known
هذه عبارة عن جزء بسيط
as smart materials.
مما يعرف بالمواد الذكية.
In a few years, they will be in many of the objects
خلال سنوات قليلة ستكون في كثير من الاشياء
and technologies we use on a daily basis.
والتكنولوجيا التي نستخدمها يوميا.
We may not yet have the flying cars science fiction promised us,
قد لا يكون لدينا السيارات الطائرة التي وعدنا بها الخيال العلمي
but we can have walls that change color
لكن لدينا حوائط تغير لونها
depending on temperature,
اعتمادا على درجة الحرارة
keyboards that roll up,
لوحات مفاتيح تلف،
and windows that become opaque at the flick of a switch.
ونوافذ تصبح معتمة بحركة مفتاح.
So I'm a social scientist by training,
اذا انا عالمة اجتماعية بالتدريب,
so why am I here today talking about smart materials?
اذا لماذا انا هنا اليوم اتحدث عن المواد الذكية؟
Well first of all, because I am a maker.
حسنا اولا لانني انا صانعة
I'm curious about how things work
انا فضولة حول كيف تعمل الاشياء
and how they are made,
وكيف تصنع
but also because I believe we should have a deeper understanding
لكن ايضا لانني اؤمن اننا يجب ان يكون لدينا فهم اعمق
of the components that make up our world,
للمواد التي تصنع عالمنا
and right now, we don't know enough about
والان لا نعرف كفاية عن
these high-tech composites our future will be made of.
هذه المكونات عالية التقنية التي سيصنع منها مستقبلنا.
Smart materials are hard to obtain in small quantities.
المواد الذكية صعب الحصول عليها بكميات صغيرة.
There's barely any information available on how to use them,
هنالك بالكاد اي معلومات متوفرة حول كيفية استخدامها,
and very little is said about how they are produced.
والقليل جدا يقال عن كيفية إنتاجها.
So for now, they exist mostly in this realm
حتى الآن، هي موجودة في الغالب في مجال
of trade secrets and patents
الأسرار التجارية وبراءات الاختراع
only universities and corporations have access to.
فقط الجامعات والشركات لديها الوصول اليها.
So a little over three years ago, Kirsty Boyle and I
اذا قبل اكثر قليلا من ثلاث سنوات، كريستس بويل وانا
started a project we called Open Materials.
بدانا مشروع اطلقنا عليه اسم المواد المفتوحة
It's a website where we,
انه موقع على الانترنت حيث
and anyone else who wants to join us,
نحن واي شخص يود الانضمام الينا
share experiments, publish information,
مشاركة التجارب، نشر المعلومات
encourage others to contribute whenever they can,
وتشجيع الاخرين على المشاركة متى ما استطاعوا
and aggregate resources such as research papers
وجمع المصادر مثل الاوراق البحثية
and tutorials by other makers like ourselves.
والدروس من صناع اخرين مثلنا.
We would like it to become a large,
نريده ان يصبح
collectively generated database
قاعدة بيانات كبيرة ولّدت بشكل جماعي
of do-it-yourself information on smart materials.
من معلومات اصنعها بنفسك حول المواد الذكية
But why should we care
لكن لماذا يجب ان نهتم
how smart materials work and what they are made of?
بكيف تعمل المواد الذكية ومم تصنع ؟
First of all, because we can't shape what we don't understand,
اولا لاننا لا نستطيع ان نشكل ما لا نفهمه،
and what we don't understand and use
وما لا نفهمه ونستخدمه
ends up shaping us.
ينتهي به المطاف الى تشكيلنا نحن
The objects we use, the clothes we wear,
الاغراض التي نستخدمها، الملابس التي نرتديها
the houses we live in, all have a profound impact
المنازل التي نعيش فيها، كلها لديها اثر عميق
on our behavior, health and quality of life.
على تصرفاتنا، صحتنا ونوعية حياتنا.
So if we are to live in a world made of smart materials,
اذا اذا اردنا ان نعيش مصنوع من المواد الذكية
we should know and understand them.
يجب ان نعرفها ونفهمها.
Secondly, and just as important,
ثانيا وبنفس الاهمية
innovation has always been fueled by tinkerers.
تغذيه الابتكار كانت دائما من خلال العمال غير المهرة
So many times, amateurs, not experts,
اذا كثير من المرات، الهواة ليس الخبراء
have been the inventors and improvers
دوما كانوا المخترعين والمحسنين
of things ranging from mountain bikes
للاشياء مابين الدراجات الجبلية
to semiconductors, personal computers,
الى اشباه الموصلات، الحواسب الشخصية
airplanes.
الطائرات,
The biggest challenge is that material science is complex
التحدي الاكبر هو ان علم المواد معقد
and requires expensive equipment.
ويتطلب معدات باهظة الثمن.
But that's not always the case.
لكن تلك ليست الحالة دائما.
Two scientists at University of Illinois understood this
عالمان في جامعة الينويز فهما هذا
when they published a paper on a simpler method
عندما نشرا ورقه عن طريقة ابسط
for making conductive ink.
لصنع الحبر الموصل
Jordan Bunker, who had had
جوردان بنكر، الذي لم يكن لديه
no experience with chemistry until then,
خبرة مع الكيمياء قبل هذا
read this paper and reproduced the experiment
قرأ هذه الورقة واعاد انتاج التجربة
at his maker space using only off-the-shelf substances
في مجال الصانع الخاص به فقط باستخدام مواد
and tools.
وادوات من الرف.
He used a toaster oven,
استخدم فرن تحميص الخبز
and he even made his own vortex mixer,
حتى انه صنع الخلاط اللولبي الخاص به،
based on a tutorial by another scientist/maker.
بناء على درس من عالم/صانع اخر
Jordan then published his results online,
نشر جوردان بعد ذلك نتائجه على الانترنت
including all the things he had tried and didn't work,
متضمنة كل الاشياء التى جربها ولم تنجح
so others could study and reproduce it.
حتى يتمكن الاخرين من دراسة واعادة انتاج نتائجه.
So Jordan's main form of innovation
اذا نوع جوردان الرئيسي من الابداع
was to take an experiment created in a well-equipped lab
كان اخذ تجربة انجزت في معمل مجهز جيدا
at the university
في جامعة
and recreate it in a garage in Chicago
واعادتها في مرأب في شيكاغو
using only cheap materials and tools he made himself.
باستخدام مواد وادوات رخيصة صنعها بنفسه.
And now that he published this work,
والان هو قد نشر هذا العمل
others can pick up where he left
اخرين يستطيعون المواصلة من حيث توقف هو
and devise even simpler processes and improvements.
واستنباط عمليات وتحسينات اكثر بساطة
Another example I'd like to mention
مثال اخر اود ان اذكره
is Hannah Perner-Wilson's Kit-of-No-Parts.
انه هانا بيرنر ويلسون طقم بدون قطع.
Her project's goal is to highlight
هدف مشروعها هو القاء الضوء على
the expressive qualities of materials
الصفات التعبيرية للمواد
while focusing on the creativity and skills of the builder.
في حين التركيز على ابداع ومهارات الصانع.
Electronics kits are very powerful
طقوم الالكترونات قوية جدا
in that they teach us how things work,
في انها تعلمنا كيف تعمل الاشياء
but the constraints inherent in their design
ولكن القيود الكامنة في تصميمها
influence the way we learn.
تأثر في طريقة تعلمنا.
So Hannah's approach, on the other hand,
اذا النهج الذي تتبعه هانا ، من جهة اخرى
is to formulate a series of techniques
هو صياغة سلسلة من التقنيات
for creating unusual objects
لعمل اغراض غير عادية
that free us from pre-designed constraints
تحررنا من قيود التصاميم المسبقة
by teaching us about the materials themselves.
عن طريق تعليمنا عن المواد نفسها.
So amongst Hannah's many impressive experiments,
اذا من بين تجارب هانا المثيرة للاعجاب
this is one of my favorites.
هذه واحدة من المفضلة لدي.
["Paper speakers"]
["مكبرات صوت ورقية"]
What we're seeing here is just a piece of paper
ما نراه هنا هو فقط قطعة ورق
with some copper tape on it connected to an mp3 player
مع شريط نحاسي موصل مع مشغل ام-بي-ثري
and a magnet.
ومغناطيس.
(Music: "Happy Together")
(موسيقى:"سعيدان معا")
So based on the research by Marcelo Coelho from MIT,
اذا بناء على البحث بواسطة مارسيلو كويلهو من معهد ماساتشوستس للتكنولوجيا
Hannah created a series of paper speakers
هانا قامت بصنع سلسلة من مكبرات الصوت الورقية
out of a wide range of materials
من مجموعة واسعة من المواد
from simple copper tape to conductive fabric and ink.
من شريط نحاسي بسيط الى القماش والحبر الموصل.
Just like Jordan and so many other makers,
مثل جوردان وصناع اخرين كثيرين،
Hannah published her recipes
نشرت هانا وصفاتها
and allows anyone to copy and reproduce them.
وتسمح لاي شخص لنقلها واعادة انتاجها.
But paper electronics is one of the most promising branches
لكن الكترونيات الورق واحدة من اكثر الفروع الواعدة
of material science
في علم المواد
in that it allows us to create cheaper and flexible electronics.
في ذلك هي تمكننا من صنع الكترونيات ارخص ومرنة.
So Hannah's artisanal work,
اذا عمل هانا الحرفي
and the fact that she shared her findings,
وحقيقة انها شاركت نتائجها
opens the doors to a series of new possibilities
تفتح الابواب لسلسلة من الامكانيات الجديدة
that are both aesthetically appealing and innovative.
التي هي جذابة من الناحية الجمالية والابداعية.
So the interesting thing about makers
اذا الشيء المثير للاهتمام حول الصناع
is that we create out of passion and curiosity,
انه اننا نصنع بدافع الشغف والفضول
and we are not afraid to fail.
ونحن لا نخشى الفشل.
We often tackle problems from unconventional angles,
نحن في كثير من الاحيان نعالج المشاكل من زوايا غير تقليدية
and, in the process, end up discovering alternatives
وفي خلال العملية ينتهي بنا المطاف الى اكتشاف بدائل
or even better ways to do things.
او حتى طرق افضل لعمل الاشياء.
So the more people experiment with materials,
اذا كلما زاد عدد الناس الذين يجرون التجارب بالمواد
the more researchers are willing to share their research,
كلما زاد عدد الباحثين المستعدين لنشر ابحاثهم،
and manufacturers their knowledge,
والمصنعين لنشر معرفتهم،
the better chances we have to create technologies
وكلما تحسنت الفرص لدينا لعمل التقنيات
that truly serve us all.
التي تخدمنا كلنا حقا.
So I feel a bit as Ted Nelson must have
اذا انا اشعر قليلا مثلما شعر تيد نيلسون
when, in the early 1970s, he wrote,
عندما، في بداية السبعينات، كتب
"You must understand computers now."
"يجب ان تفهم الحواسيب الان."
Back then, computers were these large mainframes
في ذلك الوقت، اجهزة الكمبيوتر كانت هي تلك الحواسيب الكبرى الكبيرة
only scientists cared about,
فقط العلماء اهتموا بها
and no one dreamed of even having one at home.
ولم يحلم احد حتى بالحصول على واحد في البيت.
So it's a little strange that I'm standing here and saying,
اذا هو غريب قليلا انني اقف هنا واقول،
"You must understand smart materials now."
"يجب ان تفهم المواد الذكية الان."
Just keep in mind that acquiring preemptive knowledge
لكن ضع في عين الاعتبار ان اكتساب المعرفة الاستباقية
about emerging technologies
حول التقنيات الناشئة
is the best way to ensure that we have a say
هو افضل طريقة للتأكد انه لدينا قول
in the making of our future.
في صناعة مستقبلنا.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)